Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching The Plain Bagel. There was a
bit of drama in the finance space on X
this past weekend when we saw Dr. Gad
Saad, a Canadian marketing professor,
author of the book Suicidal Empathy, and
Joe Rogan podcast guest make a post on X
wherein he was lamenting about a
so-called Canadian exit tax. You see,
Gad is planning to leave Canada for the
United States citing the country's
taxation and immigration policies.
However, in this post, he talks about
having a sobering meeting with his
accountant about how much he'll be
forced to pay in taxes when he moves out
of Quebec, Canada. With later tweets
suggesting he's facing tax rates in
excess of 55%
or 65% when all other taxes are added
in. Now, Gad, if you aren't familiar, is
an academic who's a fairly politically
charged person. He has a history of
berating Canada and the so-called woke
mind virus. And with the past year of
51st state rhetoric and the like, as you
can imagine, the post got a lot of
traction on the platform, reaching 4.8
million views and a bunch of quote posts
with people both fiercely supporting Gad
and criticizing the Canadian government
for discouraging entrepreneurship and
coercing people to stay in its borders.
And others fiercely criticizing Gad for
lamenting taxation as the source of his
quote worst incidents in life and
comparing it to being trapped in a
Kafka-esque prison despite the fact that
he's clearly doing well financially.
Now, the conversations around these
posts got pretty political with some
even engaging in the grander debates
over the ethics of taxation as a whole,
which frankly
well above my pay grade and and well
outside the scope of today's video. But
amid these conversations, we saw a lot
of this misrepresentation of what this
exit tax actually is, whether
intentionally or otherwise. Because yes,
Canada does have a so-called departure
tax, but it's not this flat wealth tax
that takes the majority of your money
when you try to leave like many people
seem to walk away believing. So, as with
all Canadian finance topics that make
their way into these online discussions,
I can tell myself and figured I'd post a
video explaining how this tax works, how
high it can potentially reach, and how
it compares to other countries. Because
well, a lot of these posts were
criticizing Canada for having this type
of policy,
it's actually fairly common among
developed countries with even the United
States having its own version of an exit
tax. Albeit, there are some key
differences which we'll touch on later
in the video. Now, importantly, while
this is a topic I'm familiar with given
my work as a registered portfolio
manager and CFP professional, I am not a
tax accountant or a CPA. So, please, if
you find yourself in this type of
situation, do engage for qualified
advice on the topic, but we can at least
clear up some of the common
misconceptions and cover the broad
strokes of how the tax works. So, what
is this Canadian exit tax? Well, the tax
is properly known as a departure tax,
which is charged whenever someone
changes from being a resident of the
country to a non-resident, which is a
condition that's satisfied when someone
leaves Canada to live in another
country, and when they sever their
residential ties to the country. Now,
these residential ties can be up for
interpretation, but generally speaking,
they include owning a home in Canada,
having a partner or dependents in
Canada, or a number of other secondary
considerations. With courts also
considering whether you set up ties in
this new country when determining your
resident status. So, someone can leave
the country to work or study abroad and
still maintain that resident status so
long as they maintain some connection
that makes it possible or likely for
them to return. However, when someone
severs their ties and becomes a
non-resident, then we have what's called
a deemed disposition, which is when
someone's assumed to have sold all of
their assets and bought them back
immediately the day before they become a
non-resident for the purpose of charging
taxes on any assets that have
appreciated in value. You see the
Canadian government views capital gains,
which is when you sell something for
more than what you bought it for, as a
form of taxable income. Just like the
United States. Both countries discount
the tax rate charged on capital gains to
incentivize people to invest their money
and take on risk rather than just
hoarding cash. But nonetheless, whenever
you make a profit by buying and selling
stuff, the government wants a slice.
Now, in Canada, capital gains are taxed
at half of your marginal income tax
rate. Or put differently, only half of
your capital gains are taxed as income.
So, if you buy a stock and later sell it
for $1,000 profit, and your marginal
income tax rate is 30%, then you would
be paying $150
on that realized capital gain, which is
equal to the 1,000 * 50% * 30%. Now,
typically, you only pay this tax once
you actually sell the asset in question
or realize the capital gains. But in
this case with a deemed disposition,
you're being charged capital gains tax
on your unrealized capital gain since
you haven't actually sold anything.
Which yes, does bring forward that tax
payment, but the mark-to-market also
resets your cost basis and any sort of
tax liability you've accrued on the
price appreciation of that asset to
date. So, those are the basics of how
the tax works. When you become a non
resident, there's a deemed disposition,
meaning that you're charged taxes on all
of your unrealized capital gains to
date. Which is actually similar to what
happens when you die in the country. So,
I guess that's how Canada views it. We
are deciding to leave the country,
so you're dead to them. So, they're
they're settling up their accounts. Now,
politics of all this aside, deemed
dispositions are a very common pain
point for Canadians from a tax planning
standpoint. For one, because you're
realizing all of your capital gains at
once, it can very commonly push you into
higher income tax brackets, meaning
suddenly your income tax might surge in
that given year, uh despite potentially
not being a higher than average income
earner. And secondly, because you
haven't actually sold anything, you may
not have cash on hand to cover the tax
bill, which might actually force you to
sell some of your assets. Uh this is
especially common for things like
cottages, uh family member with the
family cottage passes away, the property
has a really low cost basis because it
was bought 40-plus years ago, and the
family is forced to sell the building
because it's experienced this massive
appreciation, and they don't have the
tens of thousands of dollars they might
potentially need to keep the property.
Now, in terms of what this tax actually
applies to, as highlighted by the
government of Canada itself, it's pretty
far-reaching beyond just financial
assets like stocks and bonds. With
things like jewelry, paintings, and even
collections also being subjected to the
tax if they've appreciated in value.
However, it only applies if the value of
the asset exceeds $10,000. So, your
wedding bands and Naruto posters are
perfectly fine. The tax also only kicks
in if your total assets are worth over
$25,000,
and Canadians can actually unwind the
tax if they end up returning as a
resident. Regardless, you can see why
some are critical of these types of
deemed dispositions, especially when
they might force someone to sell uh
something they treasure or value. Uh but
it brings us to the first main caveat
around departure taxes, which is the
long list of exemptions that for many
people means they'll never have to pay
any departure tax. For one, registered
investment accounts and a long list of
financial products are all entirely
exempt from it. This includes pension
plans, registered retirement savings
plans, registered retirement income
funds, tax-free savings accounts,
registered education savings plans,
registered disability savings plans,
annuities, employee profit-sharing
plans,
and many more. So, for a person who
holds all of their investments within an
RRSP, TFSA, or potentially a pension
plan, there's no departure tax owed when
they become a non-resident. In part
because some of these things like the
RRSP can be taxed by the government
after you've left the country when you
withdraw from the account. So, there's
no need to tax it at departure. Another
big exemption is Canadian real or
movable property, Canadian resource
property, and timber property. So, any
Canadian real estate is completely
exempt, meaning that that cottage
situation wouldn't come up here.
Although, foreign real estate is not
included here. This is specifically for
property stuck within Canada's borders
that again can eventually be taxed when
the property is sold. Then there's an
exemption for short-term residents
whereby assets owned before or inherited
during your resident period may be
excluded. And finally, there's an
exemption for any Canadian business
property for business carried on through
a permanent establishment in Canada,
meaning assets like inventory for an
active business in Canada wouldn't be
subject to departure tax. So, for most
people, the biggest impact from
departure tax will be on their
investments held outside of registered
accounts. And listen, there's plenty of
room to criticize Canada's general tax
regime. But with departure taxes
specifically, there's a very rational
reason that the country charges it
beyond just Canada being a tyrannical
communist hellscape that's trying to
entrap its citizens,
which is what X keeps trying to convince
me of. If there were no deemed
disposition when someone left Canada as
a resident, then people with sizable
capital gains would be incentivized to
leave the country for some place with no
capital gains tax like Dubai to sell
their holdings. Meaning not only would
Canada lose a potentially high income
tax earner since uh people in higher tax
brackets tend to have the largest
capital gains, but the government would
also miss out on all the tax revenues
from the capital gains that accrued from
within their borders. Now, you might not
agree with that reasoning, but it's why
five of the seven G7 countries and a
number of other developed nations like
the Netherlands, Norway, Australia, and
South Korea all charge some form of
expatriation tax when you leave the
country with the US itself again having
its own version. So, while Canada has
found itself in the crosshairs of this
conservative commentary,
the concept is far from being uniquely
Canadian. But what you might say, Gad
mentioned paying taxes of over 55%.
Surely that's an unfair form of
departure tax.
Well, yeah, and I actually agree with
you that the government shouldn't take
more than half of what you've earned in
capital gains when you leave the
country.
Except that's not even close to what the
departure tax rates are. You see, Canada
charges income tax at both the federal
and the provincial level. The actual
rates you experience will depend on
where you specifically live, but Gad
lives in Quebec, which is the country's
predominantly French-speaking province
known for having the highest tax rates
in the country. So, we'll focus on that
set of tax brackets. And you can see on
screen that the combined marginal income
tax rates do get quite high. At over
$258,000 a year, you hit the combined
rate of 53.31%
meaning for each additional dollar you
earn, you send over half of it to the
government, which isn't quite 55%, but
yeah, quite high. However, if you
remember from earlier, capital gains are
taxed at half of your marginal income
tax rate, meaning the highest level that
your capital gains tax can reach is
26.65%,
which is actually less than the capital
gains tax in some US states like
California. And again, this is only tax
on the gain of an asset, not its entire
value, and it's the marginal income tax
rate. So, every dollar earned below
these brackets will be charged at lesser
amounts. Plus, there are the deductions
like the basic personal amount whereby
the first bit of income is tax-free. So,
switching to normal income taxes for a
second, even if your income puts you in
the highest marginal tax rate of 53.3%,
the total percentage of your income that
you're actually paying in taxes will
always be less than this and your
departure capital gains tax will be half
of this rate. So, you can see that the
standard departure income tax rates are
well below that mentioned 55%. Now, Gad
might have been just referring to
general income taxes or combining it
with other taxes like sales and the
like, but it is a bit confusing in the
context of a broader discussion of
departure tax when you see 55 or 65%
plus brought up, it can clearly lead
people to believe that those are the
prevailing rates. But, there is one area
where departure taxes can hit quite hard
that is likely applying to Gad's
situation and that's around private
corporations. Something Gad explicitly
brought up in the online exit tax
discussion. You see, in addition to
being a paid professor, Gad also earns
royalties from his books. It's very
likely that he's incorporated his
royalty business so that he earns the
royalties into a company or corporation
more specifically rather than to his own
name directly. Now, there's a number of
benefits to incorporating in Canada, but
a key one that's coming up here is tax
deferral. Now, this gets quite
complicated, but without getting too
much into the weeds, corporations pay
lower taxes on their income than
individuals pay with their income taxes.
So, if you earn royalties into a
corporation, then you'll have more
after-tax money that can be invested
while the money is held within the
company. Now, the benefit is offset when
you eventually draw the money into your
own name, which you can currently think
of it as the second part of the tax bill
comes due, but there can still be a
tax-efficient strategy benefit there
because you can time your withdrawals to
optimize your marginal tax rate and
overall reduce the tax bill you'd be
paying versus if you had just taken the
money in your own name. However, when
someone with a private Canadian
corporation leaves the country, there
can be two key impacts. The first is
that the privately held shares of that
company, so Gad's ownership of this
private corporation, is itself subject
to departure tax on unrealized capital
gains. Meaning Gad is being taxed as if
he sold his royalty business at fair
market value. And because it seems very
likely that the cost basis for a royalty
business like this would be pretty low,
it means most of that value will be
considered a capital gain. So, if Gad's
royalty business were valued in the
millions, that alone could lead to a tax
bill in the hundreds of thousands of
dollars. Now, naturally that depends on
how the private business is valued,
which isn't a clear-cut thing. There's
no public market value to easily derive
that figure, and the Income Tax Act
doesn't define a methodology for valuing
private businesses. It just has to be
defensible in court, but needless to
say, you can see the issue here, right?
You have this valuable asset that
appreciated from very little. The
business itself likely isn't easy to
sell quickly because it's private and
and very much tied to Gad himself, and
the capital gain is being recognized all
at once. The second hit is that if the
corporation itself is deemed to become a
non-resident, which can occur when the
owners become non-residents themselves,
there is a deemed disposition on assets
held within the corporation, plus a 25%
additional tax on the net value of
properties on exit, less certain amounts
including paid-in capital. Meaning that
the corporation that was set up for tax
planning purposes can see all of these
capital gains come due,
plus 25%. Now, the purpose of this
additional fee is very similar to the
general purpose of the departure tax as
a whole. Canada doesn't want people to
have their corporations leave the
country and have those people withdraw
the assets before they pay that, again,
crudely put, second half of that tax
bill. Uh so, the 25% is somewhat meant
to offset that initial tax efficiency or
savings that that owner receives. The
rate may be reduced if there's a tax
treaty with the destination country and
in other certain circumstances. And we
also don't even know if this even
applies to Gad's situation. But this
could be an area where departure taxes
for the corporation specifically could
exceed that 25% rate. Now, if this type
of departure is something that wasn't
planned for from a tax standpoint, it's
easy to see how it could be a source of
grief, especially if it ends up putting
you in a worse situation than if you
hadn't incorporated in the first place.
However, the 25% tax specifically is
really just undoing that initial tax
benefit. Uh that 25% additional fee
could be avoided by simply pulling the
money out before you leave. And
regarding large gains on private shares
specifically, there's one last exemption
that can offer a big break here. The
lifetime capital gains exemption. The
LCGE allows a person to exempt up to
1.275
million dollars of their capital gains,
with this amount increasing each year
based on inflation. So, if a qualified
business had a zero-dollar cost basis
and was worth exactly that 1.275 million
dollars with a deemed disposition,
meaning the entire amount would be
considered a capital gain, they would
pay zero dollars of capital gains tax if
they used this lifetime exemption.
Finally, around that issue of forced
selling around private company shares,
it's worth noting that the Canadian
government allows departing individuals
to defer payment of this departure tax.
It's called the T1244 election and it
can allow people to defer departure tax
payment until they actually sell the
asset. In other words, turning the
departure tax into just normal capital
gains tax. Now, this election can
require posting security when the value
of the property exceeds a certain
threshold. Uh so, that's an important
aspect to consider, but it can help
avoid that cottage situation or in this
case being forced to sell your private
business because you might be able to
post the shares themselves as the
collateral you need. Now, hopefully this
is all demonstrating that the topic gets
quite complicated. And again, we don't
know Gad's specific circumstance. There
may be a specific ruling or exemption
that we're not covering here. But
specifically when it comes to the
personal Canadian departure taxes that
people face, there are again a lot of
exemptions. The rates are much lower
than people might be expecting based on
the online discourse, and it's only on
the capital gains, the current market
price minus the cost basis, not the
total asset value of what you take with
you. In fact, the main disadvantage of
the tax is that it brings forward what
would otherwise be a future tax
liability, which the country does to
ensure that you won't stiff them on that
future tax liability. Now, one point
discussion that's arisen with all this
is how Canada's departure tax compares
to the US, because one detail that was
glossed over by a bunch of comments is
the fact that America has its own sort
of mark-to-market exit tax. I won't go
into as much detail, especially because
it's an area that I'm not personally
familiar with, but it's a similar deemed
disposition that charges US capital
gains tax if you're a so-called covered
expatriate, which effectively means
you're a high-income earner or you have
a net worth of over $2 million.
But the key difference with the American
exit tax is that it's only charged on a
change of citizenship, not residency,
meaning that even if you leave the
United States, you won't inherently be
charged this exit tax, mostly because
the US has a pretty unique
citizenship-based tax system. If you
move to another country but retain your
American citizenship, you have to
continue filing American taxes and may
even owe taxes to the IRS even on income
earned in that other country. Now, the
US does have a number of tax treaties
with other countries, so that Americans
living in those countries get a foreign
income tax credit on their US taxes,
meaning that sometimes they won't pay
any taxes to the IRS depending on what
they pay in the country, but otherwise
Americans are taxed US income taxes on
worldwide income earned regardless of
where they live. So, yes, US exit taxes
are only charged when someone actively
renounces their US citizenship. But, the
reason for this is that the country
doesn't face the same risk of someone
leaving the country to try and evade
taxes because the tax system isn't based
on residency. It's based on whether
you're a citizen or not. So, when you
eventually sell those assets that have
capital gains, a tax bill will come due
whether you live in America or Dubai.
Now, to be clear, yes, the US tax system
is generally more favorable than the
Canadian system. But, Canada's departure
tax is really just a front-loaded
capital gains tax. And well, certainly
again, there's room to discuss and
debate those things and they should be.
Uh it's also important not to
misrepresent these concepts, especially
when things get political. Now, if
you're a Canadian who knows you're going
to face a deemed disposition in the
future, there are strategies for
mitigating how much you pay in taxes,
things like recognizing capital gains
prematurely to smooth out your marginal
tax rate that you end up paying. And I
highly recommend you reach out to a
qualified tax accountant to help with
those strategies. But, hopefully again,
when it comes to the broad strokes, this
video helped to clear up some of the
common misconceptions. Thanks for
watching. I hope you found this video
helpful. If you did, please do make sure
to like, subscribe, all that good stuff.
It does help the channel tremendously.
And let me know your thoughts on
Canadian departure taxes and departure
taxes as a whole since again, this isn't
a uniquely Canadian topic. Uh thanks
again for joining me and as always,
be safe out there.